e
e e
everyone I now call to order this
meeting of city council for city of
Lancer January 14th
2024 a few reminders at the top of the
meeting this evening this meeting is
being recorded please take a moment to
silence your phones and devices if you
haven't done so already during this
meeting there will be several
opportunities for public comment anyone
wishing to make public comment should do
so with the microphone so you can be
heard both in this room and on our live
stream
comment should be related to issues that
have or may come before Council as
legislation and should be addressed
toward Council rather than others in the
room each speaker is given three minutes
to keep time the light that is here in
front of me will turn green when a
speaker begins though it will turn
yellow when there is one minute
remaining and turn red when three
minutes has been exhausted I appreciate
everyone and and thank them in advance
for ensuring that we have equal time to
all and now for all of those who are
willing and able please rise for the
pledge of
Allegiance Al to the flag of the United
States of America and to the Republic
for which it stands one nation under God
indivisible liberty and justice for
all Mr Harris would you please call the
role of members yes Madam president Mr
Med Mr Royo here Mr GLE here miss Craig
here Miss Diaz here Mr HH here and
president B here councelor Amed uh will
be along shortly members of council uh
our next order of business is the
approval of the minutes of our December
17th and December 23rd 2024 meetings of
council second we have a motion and a
second on the meeting minutes any
Council comments on those
minutes hearing none Mr Harris Mr royya
I Mr GLE I miss Greg I miss Diaz I Mr
hirh I president Baker
I the next item on our agenda is
proclamations honors Awards and
resolutions of recognition I believe we
do have one of those this evening uh Mr
Harris if you would resolution number
one of
2025 yes Madam president a resolution of
the city council of the city of
Lancaster recognizing the recent passing
from this life of Ron Ford who served
the city and fellow residents as city
councelor city council president and
Lancaster County Commissioner and
honoring his contributions motion to
approve second we have a motion and a
second this was introduced by councelor
Amed councelor Amed welcome thank you
council president um first before I read
the resolution I just wanted to thank
all of those who are here to help us
honor the Legacy of Ron Ford uh one of
uh uh the first African-American ler
city councilman and the only
African-American County Commissioner and
I will read the
resolution a resolution of the city
council of the city of lanter
recognizing the recent passing from this
life of Ron Ford who served the city and
fellow residents as city councelor
council president and Langster County
Commissioner and honoring his
contributions whereas Ronald E Ford
passed from this life on November 21st
2024 in the 84th year of his life and
whereas Ron Ford served all lter city
council from 1975 to 1984 and again from
1990 to 1994 where he was city council
president from 1991 to
1994 and whereas Ron Ford was elected
count Langster County Commissioner in
1995 and served in that position from
199 6 until 2004 and whereas Ron Ford
was a quiet Trailblazer having been the
first black council president and the
first and only black County Commissioner
and whereas Ron Ford embodied the true
Spirit of giving a legacy of kindness
leadership and service and his work and
in the community and whereas Ron Ford
had a gift for making people feel they
were heard no matter who they were or
their circumstances
and whereas Ron Ford loved the city of
Lancaster and dedicated himself to
constant improvements for the city and
its residents where he served on many
boards and with Community organizations
the last being the Barney U Legacy
committee which cumulated with the
renaming of Lancaster Square to U Plaza
and the installation of a statue
honoring Lancaster's Olympian now
therefore be it resolved that the city
council of the city of lanter does
hereby publicly re recognize the
invaluable contributions Ron Ford of Ron
Ford and expresses its appreciation for
his dedication to improving the city and
improving the lives of his fellow
residents thank you council president
thank you councilor Amed I think mayor
sarach uh you had some words I I did I
would like to invite um Timmy kirner to
the podium to say a few words I also
want to take this moment to to recognize
the Ford family um which is sitting in
the row um Maryann in particular um you
know I you know Ron loved you so much
and it was so evident in every
interaction that I had and the two of
you and your love story are um it's just
another side of Ron's Legacy um that he
is leaving and I know that I didn't have
the opportunity to know Ron as well as I
would have liked uh but I was very happy
that our paths crossed as it related to
the Ule um Plaza and the and the um
installation of the Barney Ule statue I
um I had the honor to speaking at Ron's
funeral and a few of the comments that I
made were that Ron's warmth and kindness
were his superpowers you just could not
like him his love for his wife Mary Anne
was so evident uh I don't know about you
but when I see a couple like this a
couple that displays loving kindness I
pay attention because they seem so
rare it's good to see you Timmy um you
had the honor of working with Ron in
your role at the county and we'll offer
a few
words thank
you uh the first time I had a
conversation with Ron was the day of the
individual County Administrator
interviews with each of the newly
elected Board of
Commissioners he was the first and each
was to take a half hour he and I talked
for an hour and a half you have the same
goals I have he said to me honestly he
said the only thing you have going
against you is you're a Michigan
grd as I gave him the your point look he
laughed and shook his head for the next
eight years the banter between us
continued and although I was a Michigan
greet and fan he appreciated my love of
sports and the fact that I grew up
steeped in the games of basketball and
football and
golf talking Sports was the most
necessary survival skill in this
pressure cooker of a time that we serve
together and for years after that time
was over I knew I was going to get an
email from Ron when Michigan la lost
absolutely
guaranteed if you visited with Ron in
the last year it was tough to see him
not doing so
well as I would sit with Ron and
Maryanne I noticed the picture on the
Shelf closest to him was the one taken
of Terry Kaufman Paul TBO Ron Terry
Styer who was the chief clerk at the
time and me at the going away party for
Ron and Paul
it made me smile you see when you set an
aggressive agenda and dare to make it
all happen you go through some mighty
challenging times with each other Ron
and I were part of a strong and
determined team of elected officials and
County
staff he was most often the one I would
go to for help and understanding this
crazy political world I'd
entered he garnered the respect of
everyone especially in the most
unexpected
places Ron set the goal of going to
every Municipal meeting in Lancaster
County at least once as he knew the
board of commissioner focus on the city
would ruffle feathers throughout the
county he felt that he was every bit as
responsible as Terry and Paul for
promoting strong
relationships with an understanding
of the challenges that existed
everywhere he wasn't just the
commissioner who was of by and for the
city he was a county
commissioner every week or so he would
set out for an evening meeting somewhere
in the far reaches of the county he
would arrive a few minutes early always
dressed in one of his sharp suits and
tie he always dressed like that no
matter where he was he would not only
stay for the entire meeting he would
Engage The elected officials in
conversation asking them questions about
their issues and about their concerns
with what we were
doing he often did not get home until
midnight but was always in the office
first thing the next morning we would
Gather in his office to hear about his
latest Adventure and almost always he
would start with a
chuckle I think they were more startled
that a Democrat showed up at their
meeting than a black man for context
this was 1996 to
1999 and the county was entirely
Republican with the city going back and
forth between the
parties and then he would give us
details on their goals and concerns for
their communities
I would take notes and pass information
on to the appropriate department heads
who would be in touch with those
officials and the respect grew for him
throughout the
county that was the magic of this man
when he set out to do something he knew
that showing up sitting down listening
and then following through was the key
to success ESS he made people feel his
humanity and he made them feel that they
were
heard that was his
superpower brilliant just brilliant that
was Ron Ford by hearing others no matter
where they were he could get things done
for his beloved
City he never took the easy Road when
Ron and Paul and Terry were dividing up
responsibilities for various departments
Ron said he wanted the social service
departments the biggest and toughest
part of County
government he was determined to get them
to work not only with each other but
with school districts private agencies
and advocacy groups that had a deeper
understanding of the families with which
they
worked he was also determined
that every agency was going to be
results
based they could not simply report how
many they served they had to report how
things were better as a result of the
service trust me the resistance was
strong but as I would learn although his
resolve was
consistently
underestimated this quiet persistent man
push forward and not only made the
system better but had those who resisted
eventually very pleased with the
accomplishment
magic oh I could go on I will mention
one more thing the Hotel and Convention
Center
project it began as a partnership
between the county state pens Square
Partners the city and the Chamber of
Commerce of public private
partnership at the time Tom Ridge was
the governor and Gibb Armstrong the
city's state
senator rid and Armstrong fostered a
bill that would bring Millions into
Lancaster for the project from the
moment it started there were people with
opinions very strong
opinions and oh did we take bullets
coming in in from all directions
including from within but he Terry and
Paul and County staff stood together as
we prepared to go to the square for the
Public Presentation of the check from
the state Ron quietly said to me and
they accus Democrats of spending too
much
money I've never seen so much money
coming into this city now I'm not
complaining
and as usual Ron's speech was classy and
gracious never once mentioning
politics and look what that project did
for the city and look what all the other
Investments did for the city Ron's
beloved
City so I say to you now yes he was a
quiet
man yes he was a kind man a true
gentleman
wherever he went things got done and
people loved him for it this city this
place is better because Ron Ford walked
with us and I am so
proud and deeply grateful to have called
him my friend
we have a a motion and a second for the
approval um councelor Amed I think you
had some other speakers uh folks that
wanted to speak on behalf of the the
resolution yes uh council president
thank you uh Mr Reverend Forbes would
also like to speak on the uh motion
before we open it up to council and
public comments thank you
good evening Reverend Ford even for
being here how are you um Madame
President um mayor sarach to the city
council
um it's not hard to express our
gratitude for this particular honor for
Mr Ron Ford the other day I was pushed
by my wife to watch a movie that's on
Netflix called the eight trip
6 so unit of African-American woman took
on the task of making sure that the mail
reached those that were part of the
war one of the people in that particular
unit was a lady at the ebena Baptist
Church by the name of Ruby
Wilkerson she
taught brother Ron
Ford in the Bible
uh the Bible declares that the steps of
a good man are ordered by the
Lord Ron stood in
strength he
exemplified um his uh
Faith he worked hard on behalf of not
just his community but he worked on
behalf of the entire County of
Lancaster he
fought G ly to make sure that all of us
received um the just due in terms of our
lives and so on behalf of not only ebena
Baptist Church not only on behalf of the
fourth family but on behalf of all of us
who are part of this County we're
grateful for this
resolution and finally the Bible also
says that a good man leaves an
inheritance not just for his children
but for his children's children Ron
Ford's legacy shall live on through us
and in us until the day that there is no
more thank
you thank you very
much this time I'll take any comments
from members of Council on the
resolution of recognition
comments from the
public good evening mayor Morris good
evening Arthur Morris 434 West Chester
Street I met Ron in the 1970s he was on
city council and I was Public Works
director I recall clearly when Mayor
Scott resigned his position in February
1979 and city council was called on to
appoint a mayor Ron spoke on my behalf
and voted for me unfortunately even Ron
Ford didn't win the vote that day I lost
Ford to three a special election was
held later that year and I was voted in
as mayor for a two-year term during part
of my time in office Ron served on city
council we were always friendly but not
always on the same side in 1985 Ron
decided to run for May and suddenly we
were opponents I can't say our
friendship strength during that election
campaign but I can say it
survived we became good friends when we
worked on the bney U Legacy committee
from 2015 to
2023 meeting every two weeks Barney was
Ron's Uncle I came to appreciate that
was Ron was a nice gentle person to work
with and was very sincere in what he did
once Ron committed to something he did
his best to make sure it happened and
never created unnecessary issues we were
successful lanaster Square was renamed
you Plaza and Council approved that and
the mayor supported it and the statue of
Barney was erected rum was a proud man
at the dedication ceremony on November
19th not that long ago November 19th 20
2022 as he offered public comments along
with Governor Tom Wolf rum passed away
just two days after the tier and
iversary of this ceremony I visited Ron
and Maryanne on that on that 2-year
anniversary and spoke with Ron about his
life he made it clear to me the
important role sports played for him and
certainly it did for me too Sports
emphasized the importance of being a
team player rum was a sprinter in high
school and in college on the famous
track team at Morgan State he told me
that competitive track
along with his attendance at Scotland
school for veteran children and his
lovely wife Maryanne and family were
critical to how he functioned in life I
Vis visited Ron at his home numerous
times during his illness even though he
struggled I almost always left his home
feeling better he did that to
me I will remember Ron as a sweet he
might not want me saying this but I'm
going to say it anyway I I will remember
Ron as a sweet lovely thoughtful man we
were fortunate to have him in our midst
during this time of extremism we could
use more run forwards thank you thank
you
Mar darling bird South and Street um I
was a young young person getting into
politics when I met Ron Ford um um years
ago in
1989 Ron Ford and Mike stera we come to
council as we do now about issues
concerning our neighborhood and he said
well have a community meeting have a
neighborhood meeting so we invited them
into my house and we had lots of
neighbors come in and we talked about
issues that were facing our neighborhood
and Ron Ford and um Mike sterer said
well you need to become a nonprofit
organization so if anyone went to know
sou and got started it was under their
advice and that was back in
1989 um that was when we had council
members and the faith you probably
Council woman Faith you probably know
everybody else is probably too young to
remember but when Council people listen
to the neighborhoods and they listen to
the residents about concerns that were
bought and they did something about it
and that's what I always remember about
Ron Ford he didn't he listen
and he heard us and he acted and he told
us what we had to do too so it wasn't
just a one way I'm going to do this for
you he told us as a neighborhood how to
come together how to change our
neighborhood around and we've been
fighting since 1989 he's going to be n
very missed and uh Miss Mary just give
you my
condolence thank you
Miss good evening um my name name is
Paul TBO I was a county commissioner
along with Ron and Maryann it's
wonderful to see you
Scott um Ron was one of a kind uh we
were in effect Partners on that Board of
Commissioners which of course should
strike everyone as very
odd uh but it was simply the point that
we needed to get a job done there were
things that needed to be to be taken
care of that hadn't been done by
previous boards simply because because
it was going to cost
money and um Ron and I and Terry Kaufman
realized that the only way we were going
to get this done was if we pushed
partisan differences aside and focused
on what needed to be done and uh and I
got to know Ron so well even to the
point of knowing that uh you see my
first encounter with Ronald E Ford was
in this mayoral campaign my wife and I
managed Arts campaign and so we lobbed
all of these things against this
councilman
Ford um at afterwards he told me at the
end of that campaign he told Maran I'm
done I'm out of politics I'm never doing
this again it's too frustrating and she
said I don't believe you and he she he
said just bring he took the family bible
opened it up to a page and wrote in
there I will never run for office
again this was years later when he was a
sitting county commissioner
so uh working with him was an absolute
Delight in my in our second term he and
I were effectively the majority board
because I had a rebellious Republican uh
on my side and I could trust him I could
trust Ron's word from morning to Sunset
without any question he was very Frank
with me oh at one time he saw a
supporter of mine doing something in the
audience that he thought was out of line
he said could I see you for a minute and
we went into his office and he closed
the door and he
exploded and he read me the riot act
about the kind of people who who uh
supported me I said okay you've got a
point and then when we were done the
door opened and we were friends again it
was a wonderful wonderful relationship
he was that kind of man he was so rare
So and yet at the same time rare in the
most wonderful way so I I did not come
prepared to say anything tonight I felt
Timmy would be taking care of things as
she normally
did but I just had to to join with the
others and say we were blessed for too
many too not too long too short a time
with this wonderful man Ronald E Ford
thank you thank
you any other public comments on the
resolution of
recognition hearing n Mr Harris Mr Men I
Mr Roy I please I M GRE i m i Mr h i and
president B I thank you everyone um just
a matter of question do we have a a
presentation copy for the family we do
okay great um would you like to do a
photo okay uh for the members of the
family anyone here to speak um for Mr
Ford this evening we're going to just do
a brief photo um if everyone could bear
with us for just a moment or two while
we do that this evening
no no ladies
yeah you should come on
[Music]
than
we'll give us just a moment to regroup I
know um in case there was anyone who was
only here for that item I'll give you a
moment to step out if you wish but
you're more than welcome to St
all right that will take us into our
first public comment period this is
reserve of residents who contacted the
city clerk prior to the meeting to
request the opportunity to address
Council again duration of comments is 3
minutes per speaker I'll use this light
to time please begin with your name and
block of residence for our meeting
record this evening uh Mr Harris if
you'd begin calling uh those that
registered ahead of time yes Madam
president first we have Laura pul
Thomas good evening good evening Laura
Pauls Thomas 800 block of North
Reservoir good evening councilors mayor
sarach one of my favorite things about
living in Lancaster is that I can bike
almost everywhere that I need to go I
rely on the city's Vision zero
infrastructure at least five or six days
a week year round I've spent time in
cities that are well known for their
cycling and pedestrian infrastructure
Investments like Amsterdam Paris Seville
last October I was traveling in each of
these cities and when I came home people
here asked me if I had any hope for
lancastrians reaching that same level of
safety and transportation freedom and
actually I say yes I say Lancaster has
good bones we have lots of quiet alleys
the investments in bike lanes and
boulevards have increased safety for
group bike rides that I lead for people
ages 6 to 60 But ultimately the question
of whether Lancaster can reach this
level of Transportation freedom and
safety is up to the decisions made in
this
building I spend a lot of time
volunteering and leading
intergenerational Transportation
projects with various groups here in
Lancaster I speak on behalf of young
people who don't want to to be socially
and economically Shackled to C
dependence I speak on behalf of retirees
who moved into our city because they
want to be able to sell their car and
walk everywhere leading a healthy and
active
lifestyle my own health and Joy are
dependent on bicycling and walking but
the experience is also full of fear and
danger in my community work I've talked
to scores of people who wish they could
bike in the city but they feel afraid
all of us who bike and walk in the city
have a very real fear of drivers who at
best are distracted or worst whose
single-minded concern is to speed
through our city as quickly as possible
many of us have been in a position where
we almost get hit or we get a scary
phone call from a loved one who commutes
by bike when it should have been the
standard text message that says safe at
work for myself my loved ones and for
thousands of other people who will walk
and bike in Lancaster in the decades to
come it's crucial that the city fully
commits to Vision zero policies and
implementation I'm grateful to our city
councilors mayor and Department of
Public Works employees who work to make
our streets safer and take Vision zero
policy implementation seriously there
are many of us in the community of all
ages who are backing you up and cheering
for you to do the right thing for
everyone who uses our streets I have one
final practical note as I mentioned I
ride my bike in the city year round and
I'd like to see the city revise the bike
lane maintenance schedule for snow
removal to improve safety for yearound
cyclists clearing the bike Lanes in a
more responsive And Timely way is a
small priority shift that signals
meaningful commitment to Vision zero
policy thank
you thank
[Applause]
you Mr Harris our next speaker next is
Duncan Hopkins
good
evening evening Council uh my name is
Duncan Hopkins and I live on Hamilton
Street uh I'm here both as an organizer
with Lancaster stands up and as a
concerned City
resident I learned about the Martha
Avenue underpass sweep a few days after
Christmas the day I found out I
introduced myself to one of the folks
living there who's named Bill and I
asked him if it was okay for me to
organize some folks in support of them
so they wouldn't be swept on January 3rd
in just a few days hundreds of people
from both the City and surrounding areas
engage with us to express their
opposition to homeless sweeps as of
yesterday 170 City residents have sent
emails to Mayor sarach and city council
members here calling for an end to
sweeps
I have been told by mayor srra that her
goal is for no one to be sleeping
outside in this cold weather you and I
both agree that people ideally should
sleep indoors where we differ though is
that I do not think it's appropriate to
threaten our neighbors who are living
outside with sweeps to coers them to
stay in a shelter especially if they
have already said they do not want to go
I'm frustrated that it took this level
of resistance to stop the sweep and I am
frustrated that despite being told by
your constituents to stop City officials
have informed the folks living off of
rank Mill Road to leave by January 24th
when they've already been swept several
times the January 3rd sweep was canceled
because we out organized you and we are
going to continue to out organize you as
long as it remains a priority of the
city of Lancaster to displace our
unhoused neighbors I hope you can
appreciate the anger and concern coming
from your constituents we are angry
because sweeps waste resources and do
nothing to address the homelessness
crisis we are angry because it takes one
complaint to justify a sweep but
hundreds of voices to stop it and we are
angry because when you sweep away our
neighbors they are more likely to
die we need to work together to make
Lancaster a safe place for people facing
homelessness this crisis is too dire to
continue the practice of pushing those
people out of sight that's not the
Lancaster that I was raised to believe
in we need a moratorium on sweeps in
Lancaster City as well as a right to
rest so that our unhoused neighbors
aren't harassed by the police we all
know that the city treats our unhoused
population better than many areas of the
county but we're not looking for just
better than we are looking for the just
treatment of
everybody and I don't like needing to
organize our community against you I so
desperately want to work with you so
that we can fix these fixable issues I
don't want to fight I want these harmful
policies to end sweeps don't help
anybody but preventing future sweeps
could save lives especially in these
frigid months so let's work together on
it you know how to get in touch with us
thank you very much
Mr har our next speaker please next
speaker is Rebecca
nce hello good evening my name is
Rebecca nce I live on North Duke Street
uh
thank you for giving me the chance to be
heard tonight I appreciate it um I
wanted to start by qualifying myself I
worked for several years doing homeless
Outreach and case managing half of this
County's homeless uh from the city all
the way out East Lincoln Highway AFA
Denver New Holland Leola I can go on um
I know these people I know where they
came from I know how they got here and I
know how much work I put in going around
getting
donations when we throw their things
away and sweep them we're throwing away
our community's
kindness empathy
[Music]
compassion we're all part of this
community and a community I want to live
in that's a good look is a community
that takes care of all of its citizens
all of them the people that have to
sleep rough the people that have to
sleep outside the people that Panhandle
every day to pay for a hotel room at
night and get kicked out the next
morning people have struggles we need to
address things like mental
health uh some of these people I it
would take me a year to find out their
name so handing them a set of keys
wasn't going to fix it
um it's heartening to see everyone that
turned out
tonight I would really like to be part
of a community that loves all of its
members all of them
taxpaying um they go in the stores they
make
purchases they their incomes are taxed
they're taxpaying citizens too I
understand everybody wants to be in a
clean
environment they all deserve to be in a
clean safe environment
everyone people sleeping outside if it's
18° how's it a good idea to take the
sleeping bag I mean I feel like some
common
sense we could fix this it's not
unsolvable what we need is the will to
want to solve it this is urg urgent and
I would like us to treat it like it's
urgent um I'm no longer doing that work
but this is still dear to my heart and I
just don't want to see everyone's
kindness compassion love that this
community should be um there's a
difference between a good community and
an outstanding community and we can be
an outstanding Community by putting our
hands out and helping these folks they
don't want to hand out they need help
and we should help them get into a
better situation thank you so
much our next speaker next speaker is
Judith
Hammer hello good evening
um I'm Judith hammer and I live um off
of Columbia Avenue um I'm also
addressing the homeless situation here
I'm new to the city and one of the first
things I saw was how many people were
around city hall and then suddenly they
weren't there and now they're basically
in front of the city library as far as I
can tell and so you know obviously
there's a homeless
situation but I'm sure that this Council
and our government has done research to
to find out how beneficial it would be
if we could handle it economically I
mean from a standpoint of the policing
from a standpoint of er visits from a
standpoint of getting them back into the
economy and being working people but how
do you do that it's money right I'm
wondering if we tried to ask our
citizens I really feel that people in
the city are good people I really feel
welcome here if we ask for just a dollar
a month from 67,000 citizens and maybe
not everybody would comply but some
people would probably give more that's
$67,000 a month what could you do with
that for the homeless people what about
approaching the owners of the more than
multi-unit Apartments 24 or more and
saying look you need to give one
apartment up for a homeless person
obviously you're not going to be putting
people in that aren't able to handle it
I mean you don't want somebody that has
mental issues or um drug issues that
need immediate intervention but you
could say to this person these people
that own these uh buildings one
apartment it wouldn't cost them a dime
if we could get that much money together
we could pay for the rent $1,500 a month
2,000 3,000 whatever it might be and
maybe let them stay there for a period
of time two years and meanwhile try to
get them back into the workforce this
might be a pie in the sky idea but I do
think that our community I feel would
welcome an opportunity to get money
together in a real sense to help the
homeless people and I just make one more
comment you know there but for the grace
of God go you and I at any time we could
fall off that Cliff thank you very much
thank
you Mr Harris the next speaker next
speaker is Sean Dem
[Music]
men evening thank you council president
honorable mayor I'm here again to beg in
God's name for an end to the sweeps and
the right to rest in Lancaster this is
my 14th public comment on this issue
which I have been bringing to your
attention for over 2 years look around
the number of people Hur in and the
number of people outraged by the mayor's
unjust sweeps is only going to continue
to increase this issue is not going away
until A Change Is made the emergency
shelter in the 10-fold garage which is
now closed reported serving
192 Unique
Individuals this is over the last 7even
weeks the recently opened Clay Street
Shelter has 80 heads do the
math so I beg The Honorable mayor to
stop with the lies and
misinformation no more of the lie that
we have enough shelter beds it is not
true no more of the lie that these
shelters with their restrictions and
hours can work for every unhoused person
no more to the lie that the sweeps are
somehow helping the sweeps are nothing
more than a local human rights violation
on behalf of cruel and greedy businesses
who can't stand the sight of poor people
near them and another sweep is being
schemed up by the city for the people
off of rank Mill Road which has already
been sweeped four times this fall whacka
Style no success in getting these people
anything better go ask any Outreach
worker even better go talk to the
homeless yourself they are also your
citizens sweeps do no good we need the
right to rest safe legal and supported
camping we just celebrated the holy
season of Christmas Christmas is the
good news that God became a human being
and lived Among Us he chose to live as a
poor and homeless Refugee why to shatter
our complacency with Injustice to heal
our obsession with with money and profit
to uproot our pride and self-righteous
power all this by encountering God
himself in the poor and lowly Among Us I
beg you to do so yourself God will give
you the grace if only you listen to his
words I beg you to use your power over
Lancaster City for good rather than this
present evil I beg you in the name of
Jesus our poor and homeless Lord and
Savior to establish the right to rest in
the city code and to stop the sweeps
thank
you our next
speaker next speaker is davell
good evening good evening to you and
thanks for letting me be here uh Dave
cerella uh 900 block of First Street
Lancaster I run hand up Partners which
puts the unhoused
work uh for sppin and get them up and
moving and then we try to get them
housed and uh full-time work but is a
long process and it's been pretty
successful and I also do uh my people on
the street where I do out uh Outreach at
night and the numbers you've got
everybody pretty well kicked out of the
city um the numbers are so much lower
with the 80
beds that uh from last year where I was
feeding 50 plus but the people are still
out there they're in storage units
they're in the woods so we didn't really
solve anything but now with the closing
of the temporary shelter I know 30 31
people that were housed won't make it uh
when when the alabon was at capacity at
81 uh we had 31 in the temporary when
that closed so they are unhoused right
away and they're in lacaster with no
legal place to be to lay down and the
elevator didn't get
uh done at the new shelter so everyone
that is crippled old and can't do steps
in a wheelchair on a walker they're part
of these people that were just left out
that have no place to lay down uh the
encampments the one under the bridge
that was the most self well-managed
encampment that I've seen it was so
clean and organized uh the neighbors let
them use their dumpster their
bathrooms they made it work it didn't
need fixed
uh hand up Partners along I've been
saying the same thing for three years we
can manage this and we're willing to uh
and so is people from the food
Hub we don't need to chase this we need
to embrace this I've been saying this
for three years and uh I haven't changed
my story and we've only gotten better at
it but uh every time we get something
going everybody gets dispersed again
again and it's up to
you if you're not going to help please
stay out of the way and let us do
it I love you guys thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker please
next is Jackie
morgus good evening good
evening my name is Jackie moris 430
popper Street I live and work in this
city and I am passionate about our
community including our homeless
neighbors I've read in recent newspaper
coverage the council's intention
enforcing people to vacate areas what I
will now call sweeps is to help our
unhoused neighbors get indoors however
sweeps do not achieve this goal in fact
they cause more
instability um and you've given these
people no legal place to go you're just
aimlessly shuffling people around sweeps
are not only harmful and inhumane they
are also extremely costly costly first
and foremost to the individual people
are stripped of their limited housing
and safety neighbors precious belongings
are discarded items such as important
identification documents medication
clothing survival gear and more this
isn't just stuff it's their home and
losing that inflicts more trauma
physical and mental health issues and
creates further barriers to accessing
resources it's also costly to our
limited Outreach workers who have shared
that sweeps cause them to lose track of
their clients or they are the ones
helping relocate people both delay
Services it's also costly to the city
frequently using police time and tax
money to no helpful end like it or not
encampments are an immediate housing
solution and a much better one than the
constant removals I also want to clear
up some misconceptions I've heard the
mayor was quoted saying no belongings
are thrown out during the sweeps and
that only police social workers are at
the site my neighborhood has experienced
multiple sweeps and each time regular
officers were the enforcers and longings
were trashed and lost forever it's
heartbreaking and not the response we
should be striving for additionally
claims that there are plenty of beds for
the homeless are false as Sean gave
explicit details on there simply Aren't
Enough beds so you're communicating to
the public that there's a simple
solution and enough housing resources
when there is not is misleading and
extremely harmful I do want to
acknowledge that shelters are one
helpful piece of the housing puzzle and
I personally will be supporting the Clay
Street Shelter by volunteering and
donating however it does not address the
entirety of the issue shelters are not a
solution for all for a number of reasons
people staying in our low barrier
shelters cannot bring all their
possessions there is very limited
storage people staying in low barrier
shelters can't go in as a family meaning
no children no pets people have to
adhere to strict time schedules that can
compete with employment and step towards
self-sufficiency there is also no
guaranteed spot or bed and shelters
often come with safety issues to
belongings and to people it's not a
solution for all instead of sweeps I
urge this Council to explore more
compassionate Solutions such as
designated encampments actually making
it legal legal excuse me to sleep
outdoors in specified areas a right to
rest when infrastructure sanitation
restrooms this would provide a safer
more dignified space for people while we
continue working on more long-term
Housing Solutions that meet the needs of
all and we need a lot of time to do that
so we need an immediate solution guys I
apologize but we've reached three
minutes a little bit ago okay I just
have two more sentences it would also
allow the city to strategize where is
safest for all parties for this
encampment to exist sweeps don't make
people disappear here and they don't
solve the problem or help it they create
more thank
you yes Madam president the next speaker
is Kayla
Mahoney good evening hi good
evening hi my name is Kayla and I'm a
resident of soe and a lover of the city
and its people I'm also someone who does
child care pet sitting Mutual Aid
gardening and when I have the
inclination
writing with each of these things I do
not have the ability to follow best if I
do not have the ability to follow best
practices in my work I pass the torch to
someone who
can when I hit the limits of my
knowledge and experience I ask for help
from people who are the best suited to
address what I cannot
council members I do not expect you to
perform with
perfection nor do I expect you to have
all the answers what I do expect is that
you recognize when you are operating
outside of your
scope and when it comes to the
encampment sweeps I believe you are
doing just that operating outside of
your
scope encampment sweeps are
lazy they remind me of parents hitting
their children children because they
cannot think of another way to
communicate with their
child parents who may love their
children but when faced with the limit
of their knowledge choose violence and
coercion and we have learned hitting
children does not bring about the
results sought after hitting is lazy
it's punitive uncreative
counterproductive and let me repeat it
deters us from the solution we want
while creating new
problems and so do these encampment
sweeps
I know your public claim for the
encampment sweeps is for the safety and
well-being of the people out on the
streets a sort of I hit them because I
want them to do what I say because I
know it's best sort of mentality but
that is not your place what to decide
what is best for them what I see and
what people see when you strip them of
their rights to self-determination their
homes their personal belongings they see
a violent shortsighted attempt at
disappearing them an attempt
disappearing them and their Impressions
on the city without putting in the
effort a real solution
demands I will not say the solution is
easy but it is simple this is a
contemporary National crisis Uncharted
but
solvable a crisis with a cacophony of
systemic causes a crisis that Demands a
symphony of
solutions solutions that embody
compassion and employe harm reduction
that usher in culture Al shifts and
require actual
investment what I will say is that the
folks on the ground experiencing
homelessness and folks doing harm
reduction work many of which you are
lucky to have before you in this room
have a lot of insight as to what
infrastructure and resources are
needed and let me tell you they don't
involve cops and
dumpsters I do not ask you to perform
perfectly or have all the answers but I
do ask that you work within your scope
to Corral the proper resources and hand
them over to the proper people in this
city who have a more compassionate
long-term approach than you or the
police we cannot keep hitting our kids
and expecting different results and we
cannot sweeping encampments and
expecting homeless people to vanish
thank you
our next speaker please next speaker is
Ahad
saki okay if we both good evening good
evening my name is Gary Olsson and my
name is Ahmed Zaki and we're both on uh
Beaver Street we're going a little off
of the topic here tonight and my heart
is breaking listening to all this but um
we are here we had a restaurant we owned
a restaurant on Queen Street called the
Kebab
Station uh we lost the restaurant due to
the owner's neglect of the building and
Lancaster City inspectors turning a
blind eye for 22 years that this man
owned that
building it was condemned because it was
not safe to be in anymore that didn't
happen
overnight um we really we have been
fighting for 3 years we have been
Consulting lawyers several of them have
left to pursue other things it's the
last attorney we had had a conflict
because we were talking about the city
they represent the city we can't find
Justice we cannot afford our day in
court the last attorney that we had told
us it would be in the six figures
$100,000 and we're looking for
$150,000 in losses in Damages our
equipment our food our reputation our
name we I have not had a job since then
and ahad's been doing odd jobs here and
there since then um this has just gone
on too long we've reached out to every
news Outlet we have reached out to
Lancaster uh LMP to the Watchdog six
times we have been ignored by everyone
that we have reached out to when we
just we decided okay we're going to file
this case ourselves EXA go to Google and
I put in L Bar Association everything
that came up all said Pro offering pro
bono and we didn't want to retain an
attorney again we wanted someone to sit
with us and make sure that we were
filling out this form correctly and we
couldn't do that and I'm
sorry
yes he explain a lot of things but one
things I'm trying to tell you this is my
first time that I'm talking behind a mic
it's
difficult but yeah first I come to this
country I was thinking that I will not
face with the
Justice this country is a flagger of
democracy flaggers of human
right and we will not have any problem
with the
justice but unfortunately this is the
second time that I'm facing I cannot get
Justice I have to buy Justice not get
Justice asking justce just not get
ask not get ask Justice just asking
asking for justice have to buy that more
than what you lost this is the problem
it is mean no money no justice then
where is good Justice I'm asking you and
asking the government that you're the
flagger of democracy and you selling the
human right Justice to other country as
I come from other country I saw you
selling human right Justice to other
country forcing other country to buy
Justice
but right now I I cannot see Justice
where I if if I we cannot get Jus from
the court where we to
go where we have to go just simple we
the court is a business for the
lawyers for prot Rich they making money
a lot of money and we cannot even we
cannot offer to ask our right and we are
happy that oh we are living in a Justice
country oh we are are good I I apologize
uh we've gone over 3 minutes and I do I
I there is a second public comment
period but I think that there is more of
a conversation that needs to be had Mr
Harris you have Mr zaki's contact
information is that correct okay yeah
there is a lot of a lot of things maybe
next next time we'll come and comment I
about the Justice
again and maybe the next time we can
explain a little more but but again we
asking where we go get Justice I will I
will reach out to you separately
from this meeting and I appreciate you
being here thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker
please is Susan tro
here I do not see her uh we do have a
second public comment period perhaps
you'll be here for that uh our next
speaker Mr
Harris Scott Harvey
Harvey good evening good evening my name
is Scott Harvey I live at the uh 700
block of North Franklin Street um
recently the city had planned to sweep
an encampment of a couple gentlemen
under a bridge that was are spoken about
tonight um this was just a few blocks
from my address um thankfully this sweep
did not happen um and these people now
thanks to the food bank have temporary
housing however I fear that the city
still sees sweeps as um one of the only
answers and that we'll continue to see
them planned and carried out um in the
sweeping process people lose not only
their uh homes their encampments but
their belongings including important
documents survival gear and
irreplaceable
momentos I implore the city council to
put an end to sweeps and instead work on
new ordinances that do not strip away
the humanity and lives of the unhoused
instead we need new or
ordinances in shining a right to rest
for every person sweeps as well as
hostile architecture are dehumanizing
and have no place here in Lancaster
thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker next
speaker is Mike
silk
Mike no I do not see him oh I'm
sorry good evening good evening Mr shook
can't be here tonight but I'm GNA uh
read his comment for him thank you you
could give your name and of residents
for the yes uh my name is Ned Kenda and
I live on the 300 block of Orange Street
West Street um yeah so this is Mr sh's
comment as a Lancaster C City resident
and member of the community I continue
to learn about the ongoing lack of
affordable housing in our neighborhoods
and the livid experiences of our own
house neighbors I'm deeply moved and
challenged by the number of
organizations staff and volunteers
working tirelessly to provide shelter
for our unhoused sisters and brothers in
the midst of a brutally cold
winter along with numerous others I urge
the city to cease ongoing sweeps which
leave our residents vulnerable to
Unthinkable cold and the loss of their
most important belongings we ask for a
continued and ongoing commitment to find
immediate short and long-term solutions
that Center the humanity dignity and
lived experience of our UNH house
neighbors thank you thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker please
yes Madam president uh next is Ashley
Argo good evening good evening um I'm
Alicia argot I live on South Pearl
Street and I'm speaking to ask city
council to stop the sweeps of places
where our unhoused neighbors are living
I think we can agree that we don't want
our neighbors to have to live outside
especially in the temperatures we're
currently experiencing and I think we
all know that our city has a serious
lack of housing particularly affordable
housing so sadly many people have no
other feasible option but to sleep
outside somewhere we should be putting
our energy and resources is towards
developing more affordable housing
Solutions not forcibly removing people
from public spaces because seeing them
there makes some of us uncomfortable or
throwing away their possessions which
may be all that they own forcing people
to go elsewhere just makes it harder for
them to access the resources they need
and throwing away their possessions can
put them back to square one in trying to
find somewhere more sustainable to live
as someone who identifies as a Christian
and who is trying to follow Jesus
believe that every human life has equal
value and should be treated as such that
we have a responsibility to care for
each other especially those who have
little wealth or power and that how we
treat these people reflects something
deep and significant about who we are as
people and for people of Faith caring
for and about people is how we show our
love for God thank you
Harris our next speaker please next is
uh trell
dubit good evening good evening um trell
duet's 400 block of College Avenue um I
don't believe that there's anything that
I could say about the sweeps or uh the
house housing crisis that we have in the
county that hasn't already been said um
what I can share is um
just how uh deeply you know painful it
is to hear that this is how our our
neighbors and our fellow citizens are
being
treated
um I was uh born in St Joseph's I live a
block and a half um from there I work uh
in Liberty Place um you know this has
been my home for a very long time and
you know it it has always felt like you
know this is a place where care is going
to come before Co coercion when it comes
to those less fortunate and so um I just
would love to ask like what will it take
right now like what would it really take
to make these sweeps
stop like what is it that you need what
is it that we
need to to
Route the the finances that would go
into the sweeps into a fund into an
emergency fund into other services that
could help these folks as people have
mentioned I mean some of these people
are carrying the last pieces of their
prior lives heirlooms tiny trinkets from
a life where they felt that they were
going to be honored and respected and
and be able to live in a dignified way
and to have their lives you know and you
know these these prized small
possessions and their medical equipment
and you know all the things that they
need to live their lives to just be
thrown away is just heartbreaking you
know and I'm sure that you all know that
the the the um demographic of people who
are becoming houseless at the highest
rate are
seniors and so these are these are
people who have been brothers and
sisters and aunties and grandmas and
parents and like I just I would love to
just take a moment and please like
listen to to your hearts listen and to
what we are saying and just like let us
know and and please be moved by what it
is that you feel that you need to please
end the sweeps and treat our fellow
citizens with dignity thank you thank
you
our next speaker next is Tony
dastra go Tony yeah good
evening good evening uh Tony Dash 700
Block in New Holland Avenue I like to
pack these in so I'll get the easy one
out of the way of this uh bike Lanes we
put them in we have to maintain them we
need to keep them as clear as we as we
reasonably keep the other roadway or we
need to to manage them by closing them
down what's happening is straight up
neglect and I can imagine that if
someone or someone's property is harmed
in part due to ICC bike Lanes it would
leave the city open to liability as if
the general maintenance of the regular
Street was to wait for the snow to melt
um these lanes were put in in part
because it argues for more safety and
access for people and I in part focused
on economic access as part of a guiding
principle in our plan uh some vulnerable
people use them for work even when we
don't maintain them we have potentially
reduced their access maybe not legally
since they can use the vehicle Lane but
we are now saying that's safe or just
the safest option right now if the
argument is that the lanes increase
usage because they increase safety then
we have to prioritize this safety all
year round it's as if we went in for
evision zero laudations with zero vision
for maintenance it's a bad example to
set for this policy
to the other point that seems most
people are here for tonight um to the
point about maintaining infrastructure
I'm not going to make the same request
that you open up station 6 as a shelter
immediately tonight it clearly seems
that we have trouble maintaining
physical
infrastructure however and this is where
I start to amend for my written notes
Here uh there are steps we can take and
we need to stop treating people like
tumble
weeds I don't mind putting seeds in the
right soil but I do mind throwing them
around aimlessly to the wind unless
unless that's their natural way to be
dispersed uh we clearly have trouble
maintaining infrastructure uh so as much
as I want to see new shelters my
expectation bar is pretty low there what
I do think we can handle what is not
novel is the hiring of more police
social workers uh policing isn't always
the most ideal option to approach these
populations but I do think it's
pragmatic and it's already in line with
the city's tools uh but these social
work need to act like gardeners they
have to figure out uh how many plants
for how much sun who thrives in the
shade how much water is necessary who
survives in drought we need to be more
mindful more compassionate and frankly I
do believe using the police social
workers will help they make this more
scientific maybe even the result-based
approach like we've heard mentioned
earlier so I'll cut the rest of my
statements to go right to the
end if we want to use the words unhoused
residents we need to treat them like
they are unhoused residents not like
they are homeless the city if they want
it to be their home can be their home
and that's the distinction in the two
words for me it's not quite synonymous
but it's close if we consider these to
be residents we need to consider them to
be residents and give them more respect
if we want to call ourselves a welcoming
City we need to be more intensive about
following our comp PL guiding principles
and ensure that welcome is extended to
people without rofes over their head as
well stop the sweeps maintain the bikee
lanes there is overlap in doing
both Harris our next speaker yes mam
president next is Ned
CMS I have signed up in order to read Mr
shook statement but I already did that
okay thank you very much uh the next
speaker then Mr Harris d
Miller
Miller good evening hello Council and
everybody behind
me my name is Dan
Miller I live in man manam
Township about a half a block from the
mortha Avenue and track
Bridge uh one day
I've been going this way about 50 years
I went under there and saw somebody
sleeping under the bridge and I thought
what that just doesn't look right but I
didn't think too much about it uh day or
two later I went through the plump
Street Bridge which is the one close to
damn track and there noticed the same
guy I thought it was the same guy I went
around the block and sure enough was the
same
guy
uh the uh let's
see I saw somewhere North Avenue
underpass the state for a number of
weeks I was stopping buying
coffee sometimes
sandwich we became
friendly and
before you knew it there was people with
him there was up to six PE or four
people staying
there two of them Bill and and Brian
were the reg regular ones
there I suggested to them that it's
going to make a colder this was about
six weeks two months ago I suggest it's
going to get colder and they may want to
consider a
shelter and
one of them said there's a lot of
different opinions at a
Sher so I just listened to him and
didn't push that
idea I continue to get them coffee and
sometimes a
sandwich and we became
friends I would like to thank the food
Hub of
Lancaster and possibly people behind me
or even Council
who made it possible for them for a
place to
stay a question I would have for the
city and for the shelters is when
somebody leaves a shelter in the morning
at 7:00 or
whatever where did they go during the
day Bill and Brian had the bridge to get
them out of the
elements out of the wind and stay warm
Mr Harris our next speaker please next
is uh David Miller
Glick good evening good evening Council
uh my name is David Miller Glick I live
on Hager Street in Lancaster City a
couple of weeks ago Lancaster City
officials almost kicked out a couple of
unhoused men men named Brian and Bill
out of Mount Martha Avenue
underpass mayor Denine srra said that
they needed to vacate the site because
she didn't want the men living outside
in cold weather when shelter beds were
available when I read about this in the
news it was immediately clear to me that
the mayor was not speaking in good
faith after all this if the city really
cared about their well-being in cold
weather they wouldn't have threatened to
kick them out of the spot that they had
been peacefully living in for
months the fact that there are free beds
and shelters is not enough Brian and
Bill didn't feel safe staying with
strangers and they were concerned that
the shelters limited storage would not
be able to fit all of their belongings I
can understand their reasoning but what
I can't understand is why the city
thought that forcing them out of their
encampment would have helped them in any
way if anything this Draconian practice
only make things worse according to a
2023 story study by the American Medical
Association encampment sweeps quote
displace and Scatter unhoused people
compound their trauma and suffering and
lead to increased hospitality Iz ations
overdoses and
deaths um I think it's my turn to speak
there is no justifiable reason for this
practice to continue and it is time that
we start talking about real solutions I
am asking the members of city council to
enshrine the right to rest so that
unhoused individuals can find places to
sleep without being harassed by City
officials I am calling on the city
council
and All City officials to start treating
unhoused people like people not a
problem to be swept under the rug thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker please
next is Mariel
St I do not seem to
at the moment could we hear what the
mayor had to say there will be time for
comments from the mayor later I'm going
to not do that at this time uh our next
speaker then Mr Harris uh Michelle
hindes good evening hi um Michelle Hines
200 block of East King I'd like to start
off by saying that I appreciate the work
the city and Council has done recently
to provide more services for people
experiencing
homelessness and I also want to
acknowledge the difficulty and Nuance
required to tackle issues like
homelessness and addiction I don't envy
those who are in a position to have to
find solutions to these difficult
problems today I'd like to highlight an
issue that I see with the way the city
and the Lancaster City Alliance has
decided to approach the issues of
panhandling and
homelessness in November when the
Lancaster City Alliance put up signs
discouraging giving to pan handlers and
encouraging people to donate to their
welcoming spaces initiative I went to
the website listed on the sign to learn
more I read the plan which I encourage
everyone to do and to my surprise I
found it to be heavily focused on
business and tourism
interests any Focus providing Services
was clearly secondary and in service to
the primary goal of achieving a
welcoming or as I read it visibly
homeless free downtown one of the stated
objectives was inre in police presence
in BS Park in ual Plaza an area from
which our homeless population has
already been displaced this placement
has not benefited those affected but
this plan makes sense the Lancaster City
Alliance exists to promote economic
growth in the downtown investment
district and while I'm sure the good
that good work has been done by the
portion of the plan that actually
focuses on Services I do not think this
initiative centers the issues of
disenfranchised people enough to be
consider considered an alternative to
pan
handling one of the State admissions of
the alliance is safety and I have to ask
safety for who it's fine to have
organizations that advocate for business
owners and economic growth but to
pretend that this framework is
appropriate for tackling issues like
homelessness is misguided the result is
an entire initiative claiming to address
homelessness in the in the interest of
capital an initiative that centers
wealth business and tourism will always
do just that and cannot by definition
Center the underprivileged people
experiencing homelessness and drug
addiction deserve to be helped as an end
in itself not as a means to an end of
pleasing tourists and increasing
business profits the interests of
capital are often mutually exclusive
with the interests of marginalized
populations this cannot be our lens but
is it is an unfortunate Trend that I
have seen in the way that the city has
approached
homelessness I hope that this comment
will encourage this Council to reexamine
the framework that is used to address
the issues of homelessness and to ask
yourselves who is centered in the city's
policies and plans I also ask that the
council adopt an ordinance to enshrine a
right to rest and put an end to sweeps
of homeless encampments in the city
property thank
you Mr are there additional speakers for
this period there are not mad president
thank you very much I want to thank
everyone who came out to make comments
this evening um we do have a question Mr
Harris if I may uh was there no I'm
sorry Mr if you have a question I'll
address a brief question at this time
okay I believe sorry council president I
apologize um a question for Mr Harris I
I just want to check to make sure that
all speakers were mentioned uh was there
none um from uh under the name proxy
persons Mr DC yes I can answer your
question there was a submission just
before the deadline today it did not
include an address as required it was
not a complete submission so we could
not accept it for this period if there
are additional comments council
president may ask a a question public
comment period after our legislative
agenda all right thank you council
president we can present it during the
second Council period or the second
comment period thank you thank you I
appreciate that
the next it item on our agenda this
evening is reports requested by Council
confirming Mr Harris there were none of
those this evening there are no thank
you and no interm reports of Committees
of council during tonight's meeting is
that correct that is correct thank you
we'll now move into our legislative
agenda this evening uh we begin with
nominations for appointment and I'll
just make a a a mention for all council
members that um that our committee
meeting was canceled this month due to
weather so uh these are nominations for
appointments that we would have normally
heard during that time um I will hear
them at this time Mr GLE thank you madam
president I'll make a motion uh to
appoint Alexandra Ebert to the downtown
investment district for a term from
January 14
2025 to December 31st
2029 and we appoint call Pike and Kiren
to the shed tree commission for terms
from December 31st 2024 to December 31st
2029 motion to approve we have a motion
and a second for these uh appointments
we do have two reappointments and one
appointment um if any of the folks are
here this evening I would invite them to
come forward at this
time oh not
required are there any Council comments
on the
appointments oh I'm so sorry thank you
oh no hi good evening good evening um
Alex Alexander Ebert from the 600 block
of Third Street and I just wanted to say
thank you well thank you for being here
tonight we would like to know what would
you like to uh accomplish during your
term on the downtown investment District
yes I did not grow up in Lancaster but
over the last uh nine years it has
become my home it's the place that I
practice business um it's the place that
I've met so many wonderful people in
this community and I very much want to
become more involved um I am a property
owner I am someone who sees so much
going on in Lancaster City and I see so
much heart from the community here so
I'm just very much looking forward to
learn uh more from people who know more
than I
do thank you for your willingness to
serve are there any other there are
there any comments or questions
regarding this nomination from the
committee and from cons thank you for
serving thank you thank you thanks thank
you councelor please thank
you any comments from the public on the
appointments yes um I
doo do I have to say my name yes you do
okay Susie Gomez uh 100 block of North
Reservoir Street my um question is to
the appointee how long have you been
living in
Lancaster Miss Gomez I'm I'm sorry
comments need to be addressed toward
Council and not okay can you tell me how
long the appointee has been living in
Lancaster do you have anything further I
can ask if she wishes to respond to that
uh we would like to know how long she's
been living here how long she's been a
homeowner and what was her previous job
and how many community members or active
uh
associations she was involved in yes
Miss Ebert if you wish to respond to the
public comment you can but you're not
required
to like to
I you can go
online too there's a lot of people
online that need to know that yes thank
you
man' I have been a tenant in Lancaster
City up until three years ago um and I
became a homeowner years ago in
Lancaster City um I have been with my
current company PPM real estate for S
years prior to that I was h a server at
loxley's restaurant in
Centerville um and I do love this
community so I'm looking forward to
working with them thank you Miss thank
you additional comments on the
appointments before
Council Irene Grievous 400 block of
Southwest send Avenue um I would like to
uh know what the starting salary will be
for this position this is a volunteer
not a paid position oh a volunteer okay
this is yeah this is uh serving on an
authority board commission all right
thanks for the
clarification just quickly Arthur moris
434 West Chester Street I'd like to take
the time to thank this individual for
volunteering her time to ser serve on
the shade tree commission it's a
thankless job takes a lot of time and I
just want to say thank you for doing
that thank you mam hor yes we do have
two reappointments for that commission
this evening as
well additional comments from the public
on the
appointments hearing none Mr Harris Mr M
hi Mr Royal hi Mr pleas hi M Greg hi M
hi Mr H hi president B hi
the next item on our agenda is historic
district Mr
Harris yes mam
president um considering the following
applications and recommendations from
the historical commission for
improvements to properties within the
Heritage Conservation District first is
Maran Street uh Pallet Company owner of
131 North Plum Street the propos
construction of a new one-story storage
structure on the East End site facing in
East Maran Street the second is the
Lancaster County Housing and
Redevelopment authorities oton United
Methodist Church owners of 20 East Clay
Street and they propos revision of
previously approved plans to construct a
new elevator tower on the rear
elevations visible from North Christian
Street and both of those applications
were recommended for approval by
historical commission motion to approve
second we have a motion and a second
before us uh councilor Craig you have
anything to add for this mon there is
nothing to add pretty straightforward
thank you council members they've both
been recommended for approval before us
any Council comments on the
items from the public on the historic
district
items this is actually for the good of
the order Tony dasra 700 block New
Holland Avenue um there were a lot of
people earlier and now that last row is
not needed anymore um I would app
appreciate if people could get out of
the last row and I'll gladly put the
chairs back because it is a evacuation
and accessibility thing um so I am just
saying that because I I am happy to put
the chairs away so we can all uh go home
and no one has to put chairs away at the
end of the night Mr dastra uh though not
a comment on this item uh you are
correct and I'll just allow people to do
that as we take any other comments on
the historic district items before
us no one is rushing up to the podium
everyone's just putting chairs away so
I'm going to take that as a no uh Mr
Harris if you would Mr uh Mr Roy hi Mr
pleas i m c i m i Mr H hi pres
B we'll move into resolutions on our
agenda this evening item C and we'll
begin with resolution number 2 2025 Mr
Harris a resolution of the Council of
the city of laner like lanaster County
Pennsylvania designating fton financial
advisers as trustee custodian manager of
the fire pension plan and naming the
individuals authorized on behalf of the
city to issue instructions to the
trustee custodian manager of the fire
engine
plan motion to
approve we have a motion and a second
members of council uh the number number
of these resolutions are going to be
similar this evening and I appreciate
you allowing us to move them forward to
tonight's meeting in the of our
committee meeting um in this case this
is some bookkeeping and and um some
administrative work to make sure that
the signers on our Pension Plan accounts
are up to date um no changes have been
made as to where they're housed um
looking for director Tina Campbell I see
her there she is um if there's anything
additional director Campbell that you
wish to add for this item or relevant to
upcoming resolutions which are similar
thank you I don't have a lot to add this
is um simply updating actually the
business administrator um sign signature
um from Patrick Hopkin Hopkins to myself
thank you very
much any additional Council comment on
resolution two quick question
coun um would we need to rece this again
at the switch over of the controller
position yes it would need to be um
updated if there's a new controller
it and a new mayor thank you that
concludes my questions thank you
additional comments from
counil comments from the P public on
resolution
two hearing none Mr Harris Mr Men I Mr
Roy I Mr please I M Greg i m i sister h
i president
I we'll move then to resolution number 3
2025 Mr Harris a resolution the Council
of the city of Lancaster Lancaster
County Pennsylvania designated Fon
financial advisers as trustee custodian
manager of the police pension plan and
naming the individuals authorized on
behalf of the city to issue instructions
to the trustee custodian manager of the
police pension plan motion to approve
second we have a motion and a second
resolution three this uh does the same
as our previous for the police officer
Pension Plan um any additional comments
from Council on this
one comments from the public on
resolution
three hearing none Mr Harris Mr M i Mr
Royal I Mr please I M Greg i m di I Mr h
i president
I that takes us to resolution number 4
2025 Mr Harris a resolution to the
Council of the city of Lancaster
Lancaster County Pennsylvania
designating F Fon financial advisers as
trustee custodian manager of the
non-uniformed employees pension plan and
naming the individuals authorized on
behalf of the city to issue instructions
to the trustee custodian manager of the
nonuniform uniformed employees pension
plan motion to approve second we have a
motion and a second again the resolution
similar to the first um amending
signatories for non-uniformed employees
pension plan any additional Council
comments on the
resolution comments from the public on
resolution four you SC
down oh I see Mr Harris would you
advance the page on the screen I don't
see what he sees so thank you there we
are we're on we're on number
four any comments from the public on
resolution number
four hearing none Mr Harris Mr M i Mr
Roy I Mr GLE i m Greg i m Ste I Mr h i
president b
i we will now move to resolution number
five 2025 Mr Harris resolution of the
Council of the city of Lancaster
authorizing the filing of the Department
of Environmental Protection alternative
fuels incentive Grant application for
funding in the amount not to exceed
$300,000 for the city of Lancaster's El
electric vehicle charging stations at
the police
station motion to approve second again
we have a motion and a second um this
was originally to come through public
works I don't know if Mr H if you have
anything additional at this time or if
we can invite either of the director
Campbell uh forward for this one
director Steven Campell
good evening director
Campbell good evening and thank you very
much for having me uh talk briefly about
this this is funding from D to be able
to basically jump start our EV
initiative of providing 15 uh charging
stations at the police station uh TW uh
13 of uh I'm sorry uh
um 11 of which would be for the police
vehicles um two of which for the two of
the ones for the police vehicles would
be tier three the rest would be tier two
as well as four that would be available
for the public in on the public parking
deck as well well as two in front of the
police station for uh two of them rapid
meaning tier three and two of them tier
two um it's this a $300,000 Grant which
would have a
$356,000 match uh which would would come
out of our bond issue the 2025 bond
issue that we're proposing and I say
that that this jump starts our EV
initiative in the sense that there is a
an ongoing EV working group trying to
identify locations throughout the city
public parking spaces public parks Etc
where we can put uh EV infrastructure in
thank you very much Dr Campbell any
comments from Council Council thank you
council president and thank you director
Campbell um you st there this was a
grant there was also a match what is the
total amount that would be needed for
the EV project I believe it is
356,000 hold on just a
second hold on just a second
I'm sorry
656 300,000 from d
356,000 as a a City match okay so that
would total that would be totally the
amount needed the total amount needed
would be 656 th000 that that concludes
my question thank
you additional comments from members of
council May president Council
Diaz that might be thinking too far
ahead but I was wondering how much is
the um the expense the electricity that
the city will be you know
spending um it's a it's a good question
basically we're putting in the
infrastructure that allows us to connect
the the EV charging stations the key
benefit to us all is that it reduces not
only the out the energy uh needs it's
consistent with climate action planning
Endeavors it allows us to switch our our
uh sedans and police vehicles over quick
quicker into EV world as well as making
more EV stations available in the center
of the
city so the amount of energy that it
saves there's an there's uh it's
difficult to say in the sense that it is
infrastructure that's necessary that the
private sector otherwise is putting in
place and private sector will benefit
from without us being able to uh reduce
our energy
costs I I do not have the estimated cost
with me of what the savings the
electrical savings will
be but the principle behind doing EV is
that you have a significantly less
fossil fuel use it is is in line with
our climate action plan it is uh it
allows us
to not generate uh
um the continued use of diesel or fossil
fuels for our for our police Fleet and
it makes available some opportunities
for people who do have electric vehicles
to charge within the
city thank you Mr C thank you further
comments from Council
and uh actually I do have a question
director Campbell this is a Grant
application uh when would you know if
we're successful in getting these Grant
funds for this purpose well that I would
I'll have to defer to Tina we don't
quite know from this this is an
opportunity that That Came Upon Us um
it's kind of an opportunistic
opportunity It Came Upon Us uh sooner
than we expected and we thought let's
jump on it it uh it allows us to jump
start the climate action plan part thank
you I'll take comment oh
sorry yes I will take comments from the
public on resolution number
five yes ma'am I'm so sorry if you could
just come right here please begin with
your name and block of residence for our
meeting record this is the same as any
other public comment Alandra M uh 37 uh
South an street I was just wondering how
many Electric Vehicles do we have in
Lancaster my
question it's a very good question we
have more than we had imagined we are um
we have been slowly and in an
accelerated manner being able to switch
over partly due to the largess of the of
the Lancaster parking authority we have
a number of EV stations in the Christian
Street Garage as well as that are
exclusively for the use of City owned EV
vehicles and uh there are a number of EV
stations in every Lancaster Parking
Authority garage this by being able to
accelerate the the change over rather
than continuing to invest in in carbon
carbon based Vehicles we can as we need
to replace the vehicles we can replace
them with EV which are more much more
energy efficient much
they Lo they last longer um and they
have new technologies that allow us to
track the vehicles in better in better
ways than we had in the past
Etc um there are a number of requests
constantly from the public to find
opportunities for charging stations this
helps us establish the proof of concept
um and to uh rather than fo the
requirement for meeting EV on the
perimeter gas stations and and and
petroleum stations that are trying to
accelerate their access right now being
able to make some available in every
neighborhood throughout the
city thank you director Campbell I think
just to clarify your question speaks to
in our in our own Fleet the number of
electric vehicles or in general I think
I so in your answer was that it's hard
to
quantify in the public last week or uh
about a year ago we had about four
electric vehicles in our Fleet we now
have about 12 and we are continuing to
as we change over we continuing to
change over to EV as much as possible
for the sedans and for the passenger
vehicles it's um it's more difficult and
more challenging for the larger scale
equipment uh such as trucks
uh
and Street equipment Etc um but that
will come in in some distant
future so uh our uh 12 and growing Fleet
of city-owned electric vehicles as well
as members of the public would be able
to utilize these stations that is
correct in two different locations
though the the primary set would be in
the within the police vehicle part of
the garage so that the police vehicles
have access to them and will not be uh
uncharged as necessary but then there
would be two in the public part of the
garage as well as two in front of the
police station so four that can be
accessible to the public yes thank you
additional comments um on resolution
number five from the public um if you do
wish to make comment please just come
forward you'll need to be at the speaker
please again your name and block of
residence thank you thank you my name is
Julie Zug I live in the zero block of
East Walnut Street
um my question regarding this resolution
is before we jump on this money um how
is this going to commit the city of
Lancaster to an ongoing escalation of
expenses as uh as a resident who play
who pays an electric
bill this is going to commit us and
trying to replace the fossil fuel cars
which I understand reasonable people can
disagree with uh the evil
characterization of fossil fuels but
this will commit us if we accept this
money it's going to commit us to an
ongoing expense which never goes down
thank you may I respond thank you yes
mayor um this is part uh I'm just to
refresh council's memory as well as the
public that may not know we have um uh
endeavored to uh we we have a fleet
enterprise system now in which we are
are working with Enterprise to uh trans
transition out our car so that we're not
owning cars in the same way this means
that Enterprise is um helping us manage
our Fleet in a way that is reducing
savings that savings is uh approximately
a million dollars Ste I'm looking a
million dollars over five years that's
correct we are also endeavoring to
reduce uh the amount of fuel liquid
fuels that we are purchasing as well as
the need for um ongoing maintenance to
cars that have to have their oil changed
uh and so on so with an EV Fleet we are
moving in a direction um in which we are
reducing some of Maintenance costs it is
also Incorporated with no extra cost
into our Fleet share Fleet Arrangement
and the third point that I would make
about the cost savings is that the city
of Lancaster buys bulk energy um for
electric uh and so we are able to
negotiate a different rate and it's not
because our cars are our main
contributor or would be our main expense
that we paying electric it's because of
our water and wastewater facilities
which consume a tremendous amount of
energy and why those um that particular
cost is called out in our climate action
plan as a way for us to address um
trying to reduce the cost so Council
will hear more about some of the solar
installations that we're looking at to
reduce our Reliance on both purchasing
electric but also purchasing
fuel thank you mayor RI any additional
comments on resolution number
five good evening good evening my name
is Taylor enterline I'm from the m I
just have a question for Mr Campbell so
we have 11 um electric police vehicles
I'm wondering how many vehicles the city
police have and how much is that going
to cost to how many are we trying to
transfer over as well as is the grant
covering that cost thank you thank you
so thank you for the question let me
make a clarification the 11 vehicles
that we have are not currently police
vehicles although we are getting more of
those as we go forward most of those are
the sedans within the public works or
the uh and the general sedans for
transportation back and forth from City
Hall so they're they are city-owned
vehicles but not police vehicles um the
police ve this is an opportunity for us
to jump start the police vehicle process
because the PE police vehicles generally
speaking use more fuel more are more
expensive Etc and this it was an
opportunity to take a loow hanging fruit
and move it forward with the police
vehicles I do not know offhand the
number of police vehicles but it's in
the in the nature of around 88 or 90
vehicles um and Our intention would be
that rather than holding on to Old
vehicles and not replacing them we'd be
able to accelerate the replacement
process
sooner you're wel thank you director
Campell further public comment on
resolution number five uh Alexandro I'm
you had already come up for this one is
that correct yes I'm sorry it's late
and I apologize but I I need to take
other comments before I would Endeavor
to go back so thank
you uh Tony Dash 700 block New Holland
Avenue um considering this is just an
application you know go for it um
I am encouraged by the idea because I'm
a huge fan of localized energy
production um I do hear your I do hear
points about fossil fuels my dad owned a
gas station for quite some time um
so yeah but in any case I'm optimistic
about this especially in light of
investments in solar energy uh
production here or other alternative uh
energy production because you know PPL
gouges us pretty good uh in general I
mean the utility companies they love
taking our money and doing as little to
the infrastructure as possible um this
is an Avenue for the city to start uh I
don't want to say publicizing per se but
I think you know what I'm saying with
that de privatizing the energy sector um
you know some places open Municipal gas
stations uh from time to time I think
I've heard of one example at least um
municipalities are allowed to engage in
business and this is an opportunity for
residents to have a choice to um if they
use electricity to fuel their car uh
fuel their cars and potentially create a
new stream of revenue for the city um I
don't know if Mr Campbell has any
numbers on what we are projecting to
bring back for the energy sold but I
just wanted to say as far as it stands
right now with it being an application
we don't even know if we're getting the
money um it is encouraging and like I
said getting the private sector out of
the being the sole PPL specifically
being the sole energy provider in the
area um is a great thing I look forward
to and it's going to take small steps
like this for sure thank
you darlingg to 200 block of South and
Street how many charging stations do we
have we know we have 11 cars currently
electric cars how many M I just want to
ask if that's is that the only question
you have I want to make sure you utilize
your time so if you have further
questions this will be an opportunity to
ask is the answer so we'll see okay
typically comment isn't a public uh or
isn't a question answer session but Mr
uh Campbell if you wish
to um we have I believe two parking
station uh EV stations at the Operation
Center right now we have five I think
it's five that are uh at the Christian
Street Garage for for City
vehicles um and I think there's one one
more but I'm not exactly sure it may be
part of what's being installed under
phase one of the EV um
initiative thank
you thank you any further public comment
on resolution number
five hearing none Mr Harris Mr M i Mr
Roy I Mr please I Mr greig I M hi Mr H
hi president B
hi thank you Dr
hell you may be you may be here for the
next one as well yes I think so um Mr
Harris that resolution number 6
2025 a resolution of the city council of
the city of Lancaster closing out
Community conservation Partnerships
Grant Pro project brct a
2773 motion to approve second we have a
motion and a second Dr Campbell thank
you again for being here this evening um
this ends uh we recently passed our
Parks comprehensive plan and so this is
needed to close out that Grant is that
correct that is correct the the um
Bureau of the Bureau of recreation and
conservation require Ires a resolution
from the municipal body that accepts the
pro program there's basically Four
Points to it one that the project was
completed in accordance with the dcnr
grant agreement which it was two that
all project expenditures have been made
in accordance with the dcnr grant
agreement which they were three that the
plan and related materials are
acceptable to the city of Lancaster
which by the approval of the Parks and
Recreation open space master plan they
were and fourth the plan and related
materials would be used to guide future
Recreation and conser conservation
decisions which they will be and in in
fact currently are um as Witnesses the
the designs of the three South Parks um
the work that's being done in the small
area plan for Reservoir Park and the
prison site
Etc so it it fulfills the the
requirements and it is an administrative
function to confirm to to that to the
party that gave us the initial grant
that we fulfilled the requirements thank
you very much Dr Campbell any additional
Council comments on resolution
six from the
public hearing none Mr
Harris Mr Ro I Mr please I g hi M hi Mr
H hi pres B hi and
mred we were voting on resolutions ex
councilor that's um okay we will now
move to resolution number 7 2025 Mr
Harris a resolution to the Council of
the city of Lancaster authorizing the
conditional appointment of firefighter
Charles warten with the m of fire of the
city of Lancaster
motion to approve second second we have
a motion and a second uh counselors this
was brought U uh after uh would have
been the last committee meeting to me
and this is a conditional appointment of
a new firefighter Charles Warden uh
within the Lancaster City bureau of fire
um mayor SW do you have anything
additional on this one uh just to say
that recruit Charles Warton has been
employed by WellSpan eera Community
Hospital for the past four years as a
surgical technician and before that he
was at LGH um he is fluent in Spanish
and looking forward to working on our
team thank you very much mayor RI any
additional Council comments on the
resolution uh of
appointment from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr M Mr
Roy I Mr please hi M Greg i m di I Mr h
I pres
I that will conclude our legislative
agenda this evening and we will now move
into our second public comment period
this is open for comment on issues not
on the agenda again duration of comments
is three minutes per speaker we'll keep
time using the light here and please
begin with your name and block of
residents for our meeting record anyone
wishing to make public comment would
simply move forward at this time Miss
bir darling Bird 200 block of South
Street um
I have a concern about um on the 200
block and 300 block of southan Street
trash was not picked up there was no
notification that it was not going to be
picked up this week we know for the
holiday it's picked up following the
trash is out on the street it's been
there for a while um since last week and
uh no one was notified that trash
wouldn't be coming I want to know if
that's going to be addressed I mean we
as residents get fined if we put our
trash out to early uh because the city
has an ordinance but this trash has been
sitting out there since Friday and has
not been picked up on several blocks in
the Southeast my other comment that I
would like to make is uh as far as um
appointments for commissions I know we
recently had somebody from the southeast
area look to be appointed to one of the
commissions and again they were
overlooked and it's seems like it's
becoming a pattern that people in the
southeast area can't sit on boards or
commissions and we want Council to take
this serious I mean we have these boards
and commissions and it's open up for the
public to participate we want Council to
put forth a better agenda and um in
trying to promote what these um boards
and commissions are doing words not
getting it out of into the public that
there are positions that can be open
where the public could sit on these
commissions so I'm asking to you know
look at this this isn't the first time
that we're coming to address areas in
the Southeast area the council has you
know found reason not to accept people
and uh we really want that to start
changing thank you thank you
Mr just wanted to check with perhaps Dr
Campbell or maybe mayor stry this may be
related to the extremely late notice
that the city was given by pen waist on
January 11th of no pickup
um which we received notification via
text and and calls via our alert system
yes and the and they will be making an
extra uh it affected the southeast and
Northeast neighborhoods and they will be
making an extra round of pickup um for
all of the trash the properties of
course will not be cited uh for the
interruption of service by pen waste
thank you very much I appreciate that
notified your job good
evening Arthur Morris 434 West Chester
Street um I appreciate the public coming
forward tonight and speaking on an issue
that obviously are very passionate about
also want to thank Council and the mayor
for your patience and listening it's
extremely
complicated and not nearly as simple
maybe some people think it is it is not
you have a great deal of responsibility
particularly for Public Safety I urge
you not to do a c blanch rest right to
rest I think there's a lot of things
that need to be looked at one of which
is more private sector money I don't
think the city can do it all on their
own personally I give 10% of my income
to housing assisted housing type of
projects that are needed I've done that
for three years and I have another
two-year commitment to do so I don't
talk about
this without any concern for the public
because I do and I just appreciate the
fact that there's other people that will
think things a little different not that
I disagree with the need to deal with
these issues but just allowing people to
sleep in any public rideway area or in a
park you have to be extremely careful in
doing that the last thing I'd say is
that I think people should try to be
civil and I'm not suggesting tonight
necessarily any one person but I did
read in the newspaper how somebody was
saying what the mayor said was a joke I
I don't think that helps at all I think
the city has tried they tried to assist
in this getting temporary housing for
people and I sent a note to the m saying
I would contribute to that I just think
more people need to give not only time
not only offering Solutions but
providing income money to the city or to
others to make this happen and a lot of
people will say things again I'm not
speaking of the group here but in
general they say things and they'll come
out but they're not contributing either
time which I know many of these are are
finances and some of which can easily
afford it so that's simply my comments I
just think it's a difficult thing and I
I feel for council members of May and
trying to be in the middle and trying to
solve it you do have a responsibility
but you can't take the total
responsibility thank you thank
you good evening I'm pastor Mr Kevin
Brown of uh Kingdom Life Ministries 900
East King Street and I do want to just
thank the council for
recognizing the work of uh former
councilmen and former County
Commissioner Ron
Ford um having said that it was cited
that Mr Ford was part of a government
constituency that listen
to the public and um encouraged the
public to act and worked in partnership
with the public
to create and maintain what I would call
Lancaster as being a gateway
community um I've been in this community
as a pastor and clergyman
for um many years since
1997 and I've stood before this Council
several times talking about the issue of
homelessness and the need for affordable
housing and lots of different um
alternatives for people who are homeless
and
Indigent so looking at Mr Ford's
legacy and looking at the situation that
we are facing and the hearing the voice
of the public I can't see how this
Council
and city government can
ignore that
voice that sweeping is wrong it's just
wrong especially without alternative I
know that there are people that are
sitting on this Council and people in
city government that knows how to bring
the right people to the table and knows
how to um deal with this issue and
settle it here in Lancaster which is a
wonderful wonderful Community the
question I'd like to ask
is realizing that sweeping is wrong how
quickly can we expect a
cessation of this inhumane
[Music]
action good evening good evening Council
uh David moris aka Mr proxy person uh
400 Baka
popler um I'm reading on behalf of an
individual who works alongside the
homeless population of Lancaster who has
been forbidden to comment publicly by
their
employer an unfortunately cyclical
conversation is being had yet again on
what to do with the folks in encampments
that are struggling through the cold
weather and snow I'd like to try and
highlight some of their perspective the
folks in these encampments are typically
known by Outreach teams and offered
local support when available it takes
long commitments of Rapport building
time and perseverance on many levels to
get out of a homeless situation you are
stuck in as we know statistically there
are not enough beds in our local
shelters for folks outside and the beds
that are offered have different rules
regulations and at times barriers in
which not every individual is able to
access
shelter we as a community admit that we
do not have the physical space for these
folks in our communities we then
continue to use police and other
authorities around our city to move
people out of our communities like hot
potato or kicking a can down the road I
can only imagine how that makes you feel
as a person recently this has ended up
having encampments become a larger Trend
and sometimes that has occurred Down
Lincoln Highway in local fields and
parking lots and amongst wooded areas
outside the city in which folks are
trying to hide and keep away from the
communities of the city that continues
to ask them to leave we ask them to
leave and they have nowhere to go and we
have nowhere to offer them to go they
are simply trying to create spaces for
themselves to merely exist just as I
would just as you
would as a good friend once worded it to
me these are people that exist Ed in the
third dimension when you close your eyes
or look the other way they do not simply
disappear we seem to treat people living
outside like some other kind of entity
different from the rest of us I don't
think there is enough time to address
how that type of response and reaction
to your simple existence outside creates
exponential trauma obstacles and
problems what our community needs is to
lean in on the inist assistance and
solutions to create space for them to
exist the new Clay Street Shelter is a
good project to accomplish but it is not
enough and we need to continue to look
forward and be creative in our programs
and spaces we have available to assist
these folks our community members
outside are suffering and by sweeping
through their encampments we are
doubling down on their situation and
creating more trauma belongings are lost
people lose trust in the system and
local area people lose hope but they are
cyclically bothered as their guilt and
shame are brought to the Limelight by
authorities if we cannot offer them
another solution then the least we can
do is allow them to exist where they can
while we try to Garner support and
assistance over time please continue to
look forward to how we can support these
folks not send them away and how we can
continue to support the entities that
assist our un unhoused community members
thank you thank you
Alesandra maali 37 sou and Street um I'm
very happy to hear that we have a new
firefighter on the force that said uh
firefighters extinguish fires but they
don't prevent fires as we have seen in
Los
Angeles something really serious can
happen and I remember that I got uh
noticed that we had a drought here in
Lancaster for a while and I'm very
concerned about one thing the homeless
didn't start the fires in Los Angeles
none of them so please stop the sweeps
they are not the problem the problem
are the lack of Maintenance of trees
everywhere throughout the city
especially in certain neighborhoods like
mine the southeast side they're not just
the streets along the street
uh uh the the main Ferro throughs and
the streets but also between the houses
there are numerous trees hanging on on
electrical lines and the electrical
lines are what caused most of the fires
and la so just in order to make sure
that this will never never happen in the
city of Lancaster I think it will
require some money to maintain these
trees but I think it's a matter of
urgency thank you thank you thank
you Tony Das 700 block New Holland
Avenue um I want to Echo a little bit of
what Miss bird is speaking on uh because
even though I know we've added a
resident of the southeast of the traffic
commission I also think that people are
looking for representation within
Langer's historical context uh southeast
of Langster was the most redlined and
dismantled part of our community and you
know I think people especially my age
are quick to just feel as though it was
so long ago but there are people alive
today that we interact with it
experienced issues like segregation and
redlining um so I hope that more choices
for commissions can be representative of
that history uh that being said on to
this different subject I do want to
articulate further um because I did
write a letter to the editor expressing
that we change the ordinance amended
2021 uh to include sleeping again and
here's some rationale as to why you know
what we are doing by criminalizing
sleeping in the Parks ultimately to me
ends up turning into some odd form of
economic discrimination because
technically speaking somebody couldn't
read their book in the park and fall
asleep with it falling on their face
like that would be an offense um but at
the same time if someone's being
perceived to cause issues they might be
focused on a little bit differently I'm
not saying that is the case but it's
definitely plausible for that to be the
case
um some people will say well you know
you can't have people sleeping in Parks
they're going to defecate we do have to
worry about that um but my responsib we
should be investing in public restrooms
we should be investing in these pieces
of infrastructure for people to go
somewhere safely um we KN we need more
Portland lose we also need showers um so
me advocating for sleeping in the Parks
isn't advocating for there to be this
Lawless land I I agree with resident um
Miss morgs over here with um a
facilitation of some sort of safe space
I believe that's where police soci
workers can really come into play um
these are complex things I do think in
three minutes or 250 words it's hard to
articulate a whole vision for something
but um yes I appreciate the comments of
everybody here tonight and uh thank you
all for your time and listening thank
you Michelle Hines 200 block of East
King Street um I just want to say I I do
think the counil is thoughtful on the
issue of homelessness um I what I hear
often and I've heard
tonight the issue Being Framed as an
issue of public Public Safety and I just
find it um bizarre when it's framed as
an issue of safety of like the public
shopping downtown from the people who
are in encampments as a resident of the
city I've shopped downtown I've walked
downtown I've walked in Alleyways ped
homeless encampments past people
sleeping on the street that has never
made me feel unsafe the only time I've
ever felt unsafe walking around in the
city is being cat called and that's
usually anybody um but I think that what
is very clear is that there is an atrisk
population there is a safety issue and
the atrisk population is the homeless
population I don't think it's the people
who are walking around downtown being
needing to be protected from the
homeless people I think those people
need to
be protected and um we need to think
about their safety and not
only like not not dividing it into two
camps and thinking of the safety of
people shopping downtown being
primary that's
it h 400 block of Fremont Street Sean
demens um uh again I just wanted to say
have the conversation I understand that
uh you know the the fear that that some
people have expressed is that we're
creating these Lawless zones where
people can do whatever they want there
will be endless encampments your front
yard's going to be taken over you're
going to have to see all these homeless
people all the time first off they they
exist they are here seeing them is not a
problem those who aren't willing to see
them I would say they need a change of
mind and heart however I've tried to
push having a conversation you know I I
don't just want to stand here and yell
and holler and everything and organize
people to do the same I would love to
sit down and have the conversation and
if you don't like me you don't have to
work with me the nonprofits are ready to
work on this issue to create a safe
legal and supported camping area and
again we've heard from Outreach workers
some who have been forbidden to speak
for fear that they're going to get
public push back but they all know all
of the Outreach workers all of the
nonprofits who serve these people they
know this is not good they're telling
you that's I mean even Shelby nowan in
the paper is like I don't know why we're
doing this right it's not helping they
know that and so they they would be open
I know for a fact to having the
conversation about how do we how do we
set up safe campaign how do we make this
work you don't want it in all the parks
fine give a location a patch of ground
where you can have the right to rest and
it doesn't mean right to rest anywhere
there's private property right all these
things you can have those rules and
regulations but you need a legal place
to rest and that needs to be enshrined
in the city code so that mayor to Merit
it's not going to change but right now
you can stop the sweets stop the sweeps
and stop refusing the conversation I
know for a fact that the mayor's office
has put out the notice to people in in
the city government that we're not
having the conversation on safe legal
encampment that needs to stop that needs
to change you need to say hey we're
having that conversation we're figuring
out the details we're doing the
logistics so again please don't refuse
the conversation talk to the Outreach
workers and I do beg you talk to the
homeless go meet them they are people
right they are I don't I don't I'm not
going to assume I'm not going to assume
but when is the last time each of you
spent some time with a homeless resident
ask them about their experience of these
things ask them about the sweeps thank
you and God bless you all and I am
praying for you each day God bless you
thank
you good evening John GAA 100 block of
East Arn Street and I'd like to take the
conversation in a slightly different
direction what we have is an affordable
housing problem which I've been working
on for about 35 years as a
volunteer I don't like to see people
sleeping in the
streets I think the best way and I and I
congratulate the current Administration
and this Council for the fact that over
the last few years we finally had some
affordable housing projects being built
not without objection from the people
who didn't like it in their
backyard I encourage everyone in here
who is interested in this as EO talk to
the and work with the nonprofits who are
actively working on this issue the best
way to get people off the streets is to
find place where they can afford to
live thank
you Susie Gomez 100 block of North
Reservoir Street
I'm not mean I promise um I thank each
and every one of you for your time and
your efforts and even taking doing what
you do but I do want to point out that
uh
when ex- mayor art moris said uh they
can't take the total responsibility for
not doing their job I want you to focus
on to focus on Equitable Solutions with
long-term effects there are many issues
throughout the last two years that I've
been present on on and in this city hall
in these meetings where we and many
lancasterian have not only volunteered
or opened our doors to the issues in our
community we have hubs churches
fundraisers volunteers who consistently
go out to feed our school children
homeless people and I thank God for
every Pastor in all the churches in
Lancaster City who support many if not
not all lancasterian with multiple
issues ongoing until this day so as
elected officials there are positioned
that are positioned to do their jobs but
do not listen to the taxpayers nor do
they have a passion to make a simple
change such
as getting the trash
removals um I mean they're simple things
you know uh getting bike Lanes cleared
away so there's no problem
this is not something that we just heard
today this is something that we heard I
heard because I can attest for myself in
the last two years over and over and
over and over again all we have is
Equitable Solutions with long-term
effects um do we have any update on the
park cleanup do we
know I M gz which which Park clean up
the park cleanups all the parks like I
have I'm a witness for Reservoir Park um
we've seen ambulances take homeless
people out we've seen needles drug
addictions I mean it goes on in my Park
I know there was a problem with Crystal
Park I know there's a problem with Maran
Court um I'm just asking do we have any
updates
for if I may president Council Diaz um I
did get copied um with an email that the
mayor received there were four Pops that
they did go go out Public Works did take
care of that I even got pictures of some
of the leaders that were collected so
they did go out and clear that up to
make sure that you know our community is
safe and our children is safe I just
thank you for for bringing that up thank
you um and my last question I'm sorry uh
is for councelor Royal since you
introduced a trust act in the welcoming
city which is the same as sanctuary City
what plans do you have or the mayor for
the mass deportation that is about to
take place
yep they don't have a
plan thank you Miss Gomez do you have a
plan
no Miss Gomez thank you thank you guys
go Arthur moris just for clarification
somebody just said I said something
which I did not
say I did say that you're not you
shouldn't be held responsible for
solving the entire problem I didn't say
you shouldn't be held responsible for
doing your job I would never say that
and so part of the problem again is when
people quote other people please try to
be accurate it it does no good to to
misquote people there's additional
things that need to be discussed can be
done offline but thank you good evening
sir hi Patrick fth hebrank Street uh I
was just curious if the uh Lancaster
City Council has any plans to protect
its citizens against the mass Deport
ation that are about to take
place thank you um I'd like to say
something to that is there anything else
you'd like to use your time for I just
want to make sure you get it go ahead
thank you um that is an excellent
question I believe
that and not one that I was necessarily
prepared to speak on tonight but what I
would like to say uh to that is that uh
we are a welcoming Community we asserted
that assessed that and that means that
we do it in policy and that is we will
continue to do what we've always done in
this community and that's what I would
have to say to
that that's not really much of an answer
I'll I'll add to
thaty um there are there's a coalition
of organizations that have been
supporting the welcoming CT City
certification those organizations have
been meeting I am going to be receiving
a briefing I can also tell you that
there are no plans to share that plan
publicly for obvious reasons and I would
be happy to speak with anyone personally
uh about the conversations that are
being had and the organizations that are
leading those conversations I will say
that the city of Lancaster is at the
table but there are many other
organizations that have more direct
contact with individuals in our
community um that are providing legal
resources and so on and they are
certainly leading the
way thank
you other thank you good evening good
evening my name is Irene graas 400 block
of Westend Avenue I am here to address
the ongoing and deeply troubling issues
I have faced with my property at 901
manist Street which has been condemned
as many of you know since uh 2021 in the
midst of a housing crisis this situation
has not only caused me significant
personal and financial distress but also
raised serious concerns about fairness
transparency accountability of property
manner uh matters first I want to
address the issue of the overbilling for
water and Trash Services despite my
property being condemned for over three
years I am still charged these fees as
if the property were in regular use this
is not only unreasonable but also a
clear Injustice charging for services I
cannot use utilize as an insult to
injury and reflects the lack of
consideration um for the burdens placed
on residents who are already struggling
with condemned properties all while
being denied any access even basic
maintenance to prevent frozen pipes in
winter months second I want to raise
concerns about the rental licenses
for my Pro other properties I have been
charged significantly higher for for my
properties despite seeing owners of
Condominiums with units more than a 100
pay enormously lower fees that are
receiving a capped amount of only
$1,750 this disparity is is deeply
troubling and raises question questions
about fairness and Equity why are
smaller Property Owners like me being
asked to shoulder higher costs while
larger property owners with more units
are giving substantial breaks as a
result of this prolonged qu uh situation
and lack of resolutions I have decided
to place these rental license of fees
overbill utilities and citations in
escrow until this matter can be resolved
this is not only a decision I take
lightly but it is one that I feel is
necessary to protect my myself from
further F further exploitation lastly I
must once again express my concern over
the pattern of retaliation and untimely
inspections utility over billing
uncollected trash and disposal of my
trash cans followed by countless of
issue citations which was brought to
your attention numerous times without
responses it has been long and a long
fight and I faced numerous challenges
including the desparate treatment of
unnecessary harassment not only to me
but also to my tenants who end up paying
the ultimate price as many of you
already know my rental licenses were
systematically revoked in 2019 for
unknown reasons before they were
reinstated in 202 to after I complained
to city council which endangered
obviously displacing 50 of my tenants
from becoming
homeless I am asking for a fair
resolution to this matter one that does
not invoke further retaliation or
punitive uh measures to conclude I
respectfully ask for the council to take
these issues seriously and demonstrate a
commitment of transparency
accountability and fairness the
residents of Lancaster deserve no less
thank
you good evening good evening Joanna
Becker Pin Street I would just like to
offer a comment that is an exercise and
empathy we all have been trained to know
which belongings we would reach for in a
state of emergency and if you know that
those are your personal belongings how
would you feel if they were being thrown
away right before your eyes
while you're being told that this is
because you need to be safe while the
streets are cold thank you thank
you there any further comments this
period I have a question that you were
speaking
about how's how's oh J Jose ver street
thank you my question is immigrants
they are not safe here and you guys can
keep them safe because once Donald Trump
takes office on the 20th that'll be one
of his first thing he'll do and I know
here that the cops or nobody's going to
stop
ice because they're under command of the
president of the United States to come
in here they did it before a couple of
years and they empty out factories so
please this is not a sanctuary City at
all you cannot protect them plain and
simple you guys are not listening you
think Donald Trump is gonna listen to
you guys he's will laugh at you guys
he's gonna do it his way will you like
it or
not so stop sugarcoating
it thank
you are there any further public
comments for this
period can I just say one thing m
I know I came up I just want to be brief
um for art Morris um I just I don't want
him to be offended because I I quoted
you actually um I do appreciate you even
coming out and spending time here
respectfully you are well-respected man
in the city of Lancaster I commend you
for all of your services and your
volunteer work that you have done here
and I fully fully um I I Stand By Your
Side you have done a lot and I just
wanted to thank you for that but I did
quote you so thank you I think for for
both parties here and just for the sake
of everyone in the room if there's
anything further you can take it
separately off the mic I think we've
gone a little beyond the public comment
portion any additional public comments
for this
period hearing none we will close this
period um the next item on the agenda is
the report of the mayor may ro uh thank
you uh council president and thank you
all for being here tonight um I
appreciate the comments I agree with a
lot of the things that were said tonight
I also know that my role is to uh
balance a lot of different things and I
also appreciate um the suggestions about
a
um a a temporary SL permanent place uh
for uh outdoor sleeping in the city um
um I Mr jensn I'm not sure where uh
where what your source of information is
I can say that I am not in favor of um
making our Parks available for those
purposes I equally hear from residents
around Parks who struggle with all kinds
of things who have also spent time money
have invited homelessness homeless folks
or unhoused folks into their homes um
have done so much work um to support and
and um it hasn't ended well in many
circumstances um that said we have
continuous conversations we have a
homeless response team in the city it is
primarily led by our police social
workers I I think that the language
around using sweets um has a
um let me just take a step back we have
been in a process of iterating and I
know that there has been
um times in the past when uh things have
not gone as well as we would have wanted
our development of trying to be as
nuanced and flexible as possible
regarding people in public space and
their belongings has led to new
protocols for our Park staff such that
um when things are left behind there
there is a protocol for tagging them and
letting people know that if they're
still there the next day when Parks stop
come out they will be removed if we um
if our Park staff picks up things that
um and again this is a developing
protocol that we are implementing that
medications identifications things like
that they are taken to the police Bureau
we notify the Outreach Community we let
people know where they're
at we also get complaints from people
about where people are sleeping and um
that is a challenge in terms of
balancing all of the needs we also
understand that um what we have seen
around the country can devolve and even
in our own Community can devolve into a
lot of um illegal drug activity um
rodent
infestations um on and on um you've just
come down that's just come we recognize
that we need to come up with better
Solutions and I invite you to bring
those Solutions um what I would ask is
that you would lean in with a little
curiosity about what the team has been
doing and the work that we are doing to
advance and I would say that I have not
had a request for I mean I've spoken to
you Duncan on the phone but you're the
only person that I've talked to um I am
willing to sit down and have a
conversation with our police social
workers and um other staff to talk about
some of the challenges that we see some
of the other side of the uh equation if
you will recognizing that we need to
balance and
prioritize getting people into uh
Housing Shelter
Etc I want to just acknowledge that our
police social workers and Public Works
teams are often on the front line of um
working with folks that are sleeping Out
of Doors not our police officers however
our police officers do respond when the
public calls them around issues related
to whatever the whatever the issue may
be um as the case in Martha Avenue um we
are definitely working to get people
into housing we are ready and willing to
mobilize resources to support
individuals in that goal um I personally
also made phone calls to generate the
funds that were necessary to get that um
one of those individuals uh security
deposit and um first month's rent we
know recognize that shelter is not for
everyone we have people on the street
with pets
um I I understand all of that I also
want to just highlight and appreciate
the fact that two years ago we didn't
have a permanent low barrier shelter and
the opening of The Clay Street Shelter
on December 30th was
literally it was so such a celebrated
act um because we haven't had that for
decades because quite frankly our faith
communities have said no to continuing
to host shelters um we have struggled to
find additional space and I am grateful
to tfold for stepping up and for their
garage to become a space that can be um
the temporary bridge to the opening so I
just want to give a very special shout
out to tenfold I also want to thank the
food Hub which we um are in regular
conversation um with Outreach team there
as well as leadership uh the
homelessness Coalition um which
continues to work with us the pen
medicine LGH Street Outreach team
blueprints many others all of you who
are making donations of time money
effort all of it is important and here's
the thing at the end of the day we know
we are in a national crisis and yes
thank you we can celebrate the fact that
we got 64 units of affordable housing
and College Avenue facing a couple of
lawsuits and all the rest of it and we
know it's still still not
enough I know that we have to have more
permanent long-term Solutions and we
need to meet the immediate crisis and
needs and I'm willing to hear more and
better ideas if you all have thoughts
about where there is a place that can be
an outdoor shelter we can't come up with
anything we have talked to people about
it there is not the funding the
liability insurance these are the
concerns that we hear the Li ility
Insurance the safety concerns etc etc I
with Council we approved an emergency
zoning just so that we could open a
temporary shelter at tenfold this body
has gone out on a limb and done that
with and have worked with the neighbors
but please do not believe that every
neighbor wants this in their Community
yet in the city of laner we have gotten
zoning hearing um approval for the Clay
Street project we've gotten through
Council for tfold we have gotten the
South Prince Street project off the
ground and are working on funding for
that uh and I would all like to ask all
of you to support commissioner Yoder and
her efforts to develop a countywide
homelessness strategy all of those
things are welcomed my phone number 291
4701 my email Denine D sarach cityof ler
pa.gov I encourage you to reach out to
me personally and directly I would ask
Mr Hopkins Duncan if you want to have a
conversation with a group of folks bring
five people we will sit down and have a
larger
conversation I am also looking for
Solutions and I also know I don't know
who said it but this is not our area of
expertise we have a housing social
worker that is working every day to keep
people in their homes in the city of
lanaster that is something new we've
hired two police social workers to
assist and to work alongside the
Outreach team we are trying to get
funding to those police social workers
to be able to provide bus passes and all
the rest of it they all and tenold is
also needing funds for those kinds of
things that the that federal and state
funding will not pay for they won't pay
for it it's up to us as a community and
I hear your please and I understand that
we are all driving towards the same
direction we may have different UH
responsibilities that are precipitating
our approach to this I'm willing to
continue to have the conversation and to
bring ideas forward and I know that
tenfold will absolutely be at the table
the food Hub will absolutely be at the
table these organizations you know are
so committed and they need more money so
I going to come back to the fact that
the county has been level funding
uh homelessness services in Langster
County for a decade at least okay if we
want to accomplish all of these things
we need real money this summer I died
for dollars raised
$150,000 to just expand Outreach because
we could not find another shelter to
open and then fortunately 10 folk came
through this work takes resources and
your advocacy is a resource that I would
like to continue to engage with and help
leverage to advance the kinds of of
issues that we need we can come up with
an interim strategy I will not support a
blanket right to rest as you have noted
Mr demens that that we are not talking
about and I was glad to hear you say it
because it is the number one concern
that people say we don't want our right
to rest because we don't want a
homelessness encampment in the public
park where our KS play you're not going
to see those people show up at this
meeting but they call me so I need help
there is no doubt about it our community
needs help but most importantly the
people that are sleeping outside which
you all know tonight especially so cold
next Tuesday going to be like 15 degrees
we're going to be back into a code blue
and I will just give one last shout out
anger Langster needs volunteers for
their date shelter their traditional
date shelter only serves 20 people I
think is that right Rebecca 20 or less
people the day shelter and its expansion
at tfold can serve many many more but
they need volunteers help them staff it
let's do
this that concludes that portion of my
remarks my second portion of my remarks
is a shout out to the Department of
Public Works and their team and if you
will just give me a few more minutes
over the past weeks the staff across the
department have faced some significant
challenges and I just want to note the
snowstorm last week Crews were out 24
hours a day seven 24 hours a day on
12-hour shifts for multiple days to
clear the snow we have those bike Lanes
cleared in 48
hours they pulled off an incredible
amount of work with the people power
that they have and I am very grateful to
get getting the city back and
functioning as as soon as they did
secondly this weekend and this is mostly
for council's edification but also for
the public we narrowly avoided having to
send another mandatory water
conservation notice to all of the
customers last Saturday DPW Crews were
again working around the clock to ensure
the Susana treatment plant could produce
enough drinking water to meet demands
icy conditions on the sisana river
diminished the plants intake uh and our
Reservoir was beginning to approach a
concerning low level approximately 5 ft
where our normal is about 18 ft so I
just want to give a shout out to Dan and
um Todd and his entire team at the
Susana plant um and other public work
staff that pitched in to be able to
increase the intake into the plant and
restore the water levels so that um we
did not have to uh elicit another
mandatory water conservation and finally
uh I want to thank the crews Steve that
were out on Christmas Day dealing with
two water main breaks in over 12 hours
we've had about 60 watering grapes um
this last year and unfortunately
December saw one most every day thanks
to those cold temperatures so I um want
to just express my appreciation we have
extraordinary people that work for the
city of Lancaster who are truly
dedicated and I just wanted to
acknowledge them uh before Council on
the public that concludes my remarks
thank you mayor srai Madame council
president may I briefly address just the
question with without arguing with any
of her points that she asked be out
border with our agenda and I I do
appreciate that but we we're going to
continue to follow the agenda this
evening but if there's anything after
the meeting that you might want to add I
encourage you to speak to Mayor I think
it would be of interest to the public
and I again don't want to argue with any
of the points just want to answer the
question that she asked about the source
it it would be out of order Mr DC I'm
I'm sorry you would be allowed to allow
it of course right and I'm not going to
do that this evening very well well
perhaps after the evening and I would
invite others if Madame mayor we could
speak to you just briefly because love
to talk about that thank you thank you
um the next item on the agenda is the
report of President of council um just
briefly I want to thank everyone for
coming out tonight um I agree that the
shelters in our city and county um the
ones that pop up across the county
Aren't Enough um I agree that moving
people isn't a solution and that the
current housing in this County isn't
enough to meet the needs of everyone in
our community both in amount and type of
housing we see that everywhere um I do
not believe that unhoused people in our
city make our city or any spaces
inherently unsafe I have no easy
solutions or anything more eloquent to
say this evening but I do look forward
to working and continuing to work
together to do this type of advocacy for
more dollars and more services within
our community that happens through state
and federal funding at this at this
point um and also from our nonprofit
Community which several of you
highlighted this evening and I want to
just highlight something that was kind
of buried in an LMP article last week
that is crucial um the Lancaster County
food Hub collects donations for security
deposits first month rent and other
housing expenses which is often a
primary barrier to getting people into
real housing and not shelters but real
housing um those expenses they're
collecting donations for um at uh the
food Hub like Mr County food Hub website
you you can earmark your donation to go
toward those purposes they work with
people including with folks that were
living under the Martha Avenue overpass
to get into housing and they need our
help um your donations can be recurring
um $5 a week I don't know pick your
amount but it's going to take everybody
in the city and Lancaster County working
together to start working on this
problem and then come together to
actually find real solutions because
everybody donating $5 a week isn't a
real solution and I think we all know
that but it may need to be what we do
right now so again I don't have anything
more eloquent to say in my report than
to highlight that and thank you all
again uh for being here this evening uh
we will now move to council comments any
comments from Council if I I'm gonna go
right down the line Council HS oh thank
you council president I want to thank
everybody that came here tonight to to
speak um on this issue of our house
neighbors um some of you may know that I
work for the as of my day job I work for
the laner County Housing Redevelopment
Authority which houses the Homeless
Coalition which opened the 80b shelter
at otterbine and as an accountant that
looks at the money behind this I can
tell you very clearly that it's an
underresourced
system and a lot of a lot of the systems
that we're talking about a lot of the
things that we're talking about that we
want to do the the resources are not
there
they're not and a lot of what's
currently going even we have to figure
out how we're going to fund that in the
long term don't take any of that for
granted and I would not take for granted
either a lot of the people that are you
know serving meals daily everywhere
every day somewhere uh in the city
there's a church or a local organization
that's uh serving meals um that takes
hands that takes effort that takes
resources and if we take that for
granted it will go away
but you're that's all I have to say but
you're also on the property reinvestment
board condemning properties correct
additional Council comment conflict of
interest property reinvest I want to
thank everybody that has been concerned
for all the homeless I've been homeless
I know what it feels like I know what it
is to sleep on a bench and it's not easy
luckily somebody from the church did
pick us up so I can say that there are
many of our churches are probably
extended one specifically has asked for
grants in order to pay for some of them
to stay at hotels but they were not they
didn't receive it that's right we do
have a lot of housing it's just not
affordable for people how can it is all
market price no protection on rent C and
that's what another thing we have to
look at we have to look at the fact that
all the things that are being built is
not affordable to the $2,000
forro that's what so we need to continue
working with as many people in our
organizations whether it's the religious
entities whether it's other entities
that can help to find places where
people are going to be able to pay for
their rent you can put a person in the
housing but if they can't afford it
because they're not making enough money
they're going to wind up homeless again
that's so I want to thank everybody that
are advocating for for the homeless
because that's another Factor's property
reinvest additional Council
comments hearing none and having reached
the end of our agenda I'll hear a motion
to adjourn motion to adjourn second you
have a motion and a second all in favor
I I we ajour thank you
f